Guide to the Advertising Ephemera Collection, 1850s-1980s RL.00014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Advertising Ephemera collection
1850s-1980s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Advertising Ephemera. Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00014
35 Linear Feet 9,279 items
The Advertising Ephemera Collection is composed of single advertisements, product and trade catalogs, advertising pamphlets, and broadsides. The advertisements are primarily American and from the late 19th and early to mid 20th century.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Items were purchased by or transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in the 1970s, and 1990-2014.
Collection Overview
The Advertising Ephemera Collection is composed of single advertisements, product and trade catalogs, advertising pamphlets, and broadsides. The advertisements are primarily American and from the late 19th and early to mid 20th century. The collection is divided into broad subject categories, based on the primary type of product or service being advertised, which are arranged in alphabetical order. Within each subject category material is divided based upon the form of the material; leaflets, letters, and sheets printed on both sides; trade cards (mechanical, metamorphic, see-thru, shape, fabric inserts, unusual feature, postcards and insert cards); booklets; special categories; and miscellaneous. A subseries of foreign advertising material consists predominately of travel related literature and is arrange alphabetically by country. The arrangement of oversize materials parallels the original arrangement.
The researcher should note that trade catalogs that are pamphlets may be found in several places in the Perkins Library: this collections; individually in the stacks as fully cataloged items; or as part of groups of old pamphlets for which the cataloging was by main entry only. Advertising broadsides may also be found in the Broadsides Collection and many collections of manuscripts also contain advertising materials.
Some useful reference sources for gathering further information on this type of material include:
Romaine, Lawrence B., "A Guide to American Trade Catalogs," 1944-1900 (New York, 1960).
Hammond, Dorothy, "Advertising Collectibles of Times Past," (Des Moines, Iowa, 1974).
Kaduck, John M., "Advertising Trade Cards," (Des Moines, Iowa, 1976).
McQuarry, Jim, "Collectors Guide to Advertising Cards," (Gas City, Indiana, 1975).
Additions to the collection have not been processed and therefore to do reflect the arrangement of the rest of the collection. Please refer to the detailed description below for more information about their content.
Women -- Health and hygiene; Business cards; Patent medicines -- Catalogs; Machinery -- Catalogs; Equipment and supplies -- Catalogs; Commercial catalogs; Pamphlets; Ephemera; Cookbooks; Building materials -- Catalogs; Automobiles -- Catalogs; House furnishings industry and trade; Advertising; Advertising, American; Advertising cards; Advertising -- Tourist trade; Broadsides; Playbills; Furniture -- Catalogs; Cookery; Clothing and dress; Household appliances; Trade catalogs; Recipes; Health products; Memorabilia; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Advertising Ephemera. Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Advertising Ephemera Subject Files
  - Advertising Business, 1 folder (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Additional oversize materials in Box 63.
  - Airplanes, Astrology, Magic & Dreams, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Attorneys, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Automobiles and Roads, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Badges, Stickers, and Stamps, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Banks & Finance, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Beauty Parlors & Barber Shops, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Bicycles, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Books, Publishing, and Printing, 3 folders (Box 2)
    Publisher and bookseller catalogs. Some magzine and subscription advertisements.
  - Books, Publishing, and Printing, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Books, Publishing, and Printing, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Boots and Shoes, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Building Supplies, 6 folders (Box 5)
    Building supplies, equipment, and services. Architectural ornaments and building matertials.
  - Building Supplies, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Burial, 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Carriages, Buggies, and Horse Paraphernalia, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Clothing, 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Commercial and Trade Organizations, 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Computers, 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Dance, 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Drama, 3 folders (Box 9)
    Chiefly playbills for theater performances in Philadelphia and New York.
  - Drama, 5 folders (Box 10)
  - Drama, 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Drama, 4 folders (Box 12)
  - Education, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Expositions, Fairs, & Festivals, 1 folder (Box 13)
  - Expositions, Fairs, & Festivals, 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Eyeglasses, 1 folder (Box 14)
  - Farm Machinery and Implements, 5 folders (Box 15)
  - Farm Machinery and Implements, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Fertilizers, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Food, 3 folders (Box 17)
  - Foreign Countries
    Catalogs and brochures for foreign travel and package tours. Includes museum and retaurant guides, shopping guides, and regional maps.
    - Albania, 1 folder (Box 17)
    - Austria, 1 folder (Box 17)
    - Belgium, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Brazil, 1 folder (Box 17)
    - Canada, 1 folder (Box 17)
    - China, 1 folder (Box 17)
    - Cuba, 1 folder (Box 17)
  - Foreign Countries (Box 18)
    - England, 5 folders (Box 18)
  - Foreign Countries (Box 19)
    - England, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - France, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Foreign Countries (Box 20)
    - Germany, 1 folder (Box 20)
    - Greece, 1 folder (Box 20)
    - Hungary, 1 folder (Box 20)
    - Ireland, 1 folder (Box 20)
    - Israel, 1 folder (Box 20)
    - Italy, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Japan, 1 folder (Box 20)
    - Mexico, 1 folder (Box 20)
    - Monaco, 1 folder (Box 20)
    - Netherlands, 1 folder (Box 20)
    - Philippines, 1 folder (Box 20)
    - Puerto Rico, 1 folder (Box 20)
  - Foreign Countries (Box 21)
    - Romania, 1 folder (Box 21)
    - Scotland, 1 folder (Box 21)
    - South Africa, 1 folder (Box 21)
    - Sweden, 1 folder (Box 21)
    - Switzerland, 1 folder (Box 21)
    - Tours-Foreign, 1 folder (Box 21)
    - Turkey, 1 folder (Box 21)
    - Yugoslavia, 1 folder (Box 21)
  - Furniture, 5 folders (Box 22)
    Chiefly catalogs for school, library, and office furniture. Some catalogs for home furniture. For rugs, lamps, fixtures, and other home related items see Home Furnishings. Additional oversize materials in Box 63.
  - Furniture, 5 folders (Box 23)
  - Furniture, 4 folders (Box 24)
  - Furniture, 4 folders (Box 25)
  - Furs & Skins, 1 folder (Box 26)
  - Guns, 1 folder (Box 26)
  - Hair Goods, 1 folder (Box 26)
  - Hardware, 4 folders (Box 26)
  - Health and Patent Medicines, 4 folders (Box 27)
  - Health and Patent Medicines, 4 folders (Box 28)
  - Health and Patent Medicines, 4 folders (Box 29)
  - Heating and Fuel, 1 folder (Box 30)
  - Horticulture, 3 folders (Box 30)
  - Household Appliances and Supplies, 4 folders (Box 31)
  - Household Furnishings, 4 folders (Box 32)
  - Household Furnishings, 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Houses and Buildings, 1 folder (Box 33)
  - Insecticides, 1 folder (Box 34)
  - Insurance, 2 folders (Box 34)
  - Jewelry, Watches, and Clocks, 2 folders (Box 34)
  - Lectures, 1 folder (Box 34)
  - Lighting, 2 folders (Box 35)
  - Liquor, Wines, and Spirits, 1 folder (Box 35)
  - Livestock, Poultry, Bees, etc., 2 folders (Box 35)
  - Lotteries, 1 folder (Box 35)
  - Lumber, Woodworking, and Related Machinery, 1 folder (Box 36)
  - Machinery and Instruments, 3 folders (Box 36)
  - Machinery and Instruments, 5 folders (Box 37)
  - Machinery and Instruments, 3 folders (Box 38)
  - Machinery and Instruments, 4 folders (Box 39)
  - Machinery and Instruments, 2 folders (Box 40)
  - Machinery and Instruments, 4 folders (Box 41)
  - Mercantile Business, 1 folder (Box 42)
  - Mining, 1 folder (Box 42)
  - Miscellaneous, 1 folder (Box 42)
  - Moving Pictures, 1 folder (Box 42)
  - Music, 1 folder (Box 42)
  - Music Concerts, 2 folders (Box 42)
  - Musical Instruments, 1 folder (Box 43)
  - Nuclear Power, 1 folder (Box 43)
  - Office Supplies, 3 folders (Box 43)
  - Paper and Paper Products, 1 folder (Box 43)
  - Penmanship, 1 folder (Box 43)
  - Pets, 1 folder (Box 44)
  - Photography and Projection Equipment, 1 folder (Box 44)
  - Radios, 1 folder (Box 44)
  - Railroads, 3 folders (Box 44)
  - Railroads, 4 folders (Box 45)
  - Railroads, 4 folders (Box 46)
  - Real Estate, 1 folder (Box 47)
  - Resorts, Hotels, and Travel, 3 folders (Box 47)
  - Resorts, Hotels, and Travel, 4 folders (Box 48)
  - Resorts, Hotels, and Travel, 3 folders (Box 49)
  - Rubber Goods, 1 folder (Box 49)
  - Sewing Equipment and Supplies, 1 folder (Box 49)
  - Sporting Goods, 2 folders (Box 50)
  - Steamships and Boats, 2 folders (Box 50)
  - Steamships and Boats, 4 folders (Box 51)
  - Telegraphs and Telephones, 1 folder (Box 52)
  - Textiles, 2 folders (Box 52)
  - Toiletries, 1 folder (Box 52)
  - Toys, 1 folder (Box 52)
  - Utilities, 1 folder (Box 52)
- Advertising Ephemera Subject Files - Oversize Materials
  - Automobiles and Roads (Box 53)
  - Beauty Parlors and Barbershops (Box 53)
  - Books, Publishing, and Printing (Box 53)
  - Boots and Shoes (Box 53)
  - Building Supplies (Box 54)
  - Building Supplies (Box 55)
  - Carriages, Buggies, and Horse Paraphernalia (Box 55)
  - Clothing (Box 55)
  - Drama (Box 56)
  - Education (Box 56)
  - Expositions, Fairs, & Festivals (Box 56)
  - Fertilizers (Box 56)
  - Food (Box 56)
    Additional Oversize materials held in Box 63.
  - Foreign Countries
    - England (Box 56)
    - France (Box 56)
    - Germany (Box 56)
    - Yugoslavia (Box 56)
  - Furniture (Box 56)
  - Furs and Skins (Box 57)
  - Health and Patent Medicines (Box 57)
  - Heating and Fuel (Box 57)
  - Horticulture (Box 57)
  - Household Appliances (Box 57)
  - Household Furnishings (Box 58)
  - Insurance (Box 58)
  - Jewelry, Watches, and Clocks (Box 58)
  - Lighting (Box 58)
  - Liquor, Wine, and Spirits (Box 58)
  - Livestock, Poultry, Bees, etc. (Box 58)
  - Lumber, Woodworking, and Related Machinery (Box 58)
  - Machinery and Instruments (Box 59)
  - Machinery and Instruments (Box 60)
  - Machinery and Instruments (Box 61)
  - Mercantile Businesses (Box 62)
  - Music (Box 62)
  - Musical Instruments (Box 62)
  - Office Supplies (Box 62)
  - Railroads (Box 62)
  - Resorts, Hotels, and Travel (Box 62)
  - Sewing Equipment and Supplies (Box 62)
  - Steamships and Boats (Box 62)
  - Toiletries (Box 62)
- Accession (2001-0034), 1860-1999
  Addition (2001-0034) (2,012 items; dated 1860-1999) contains examples of ephemera, including: House of Lights (Raleigh and Cary, N.C.) night light, Dalziel Supply Co. hanger, N. Donald Edwards Co. paper clip dispenser, FedEx golf tee, Emery Worldwide keychain, and Baird & Warner real estate jar opener.
- Accession (2002-0082), 1960s-1970s, 2 boxes
  Addition (2002-0082) (250 items, 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1960s-1970s) contains primarily catalogs for the flooring and carpeting retail industry, brochures, and business cards for diverse stores and services. Also includes advertising memorabilia such as rulers, sewing kits, and keychains.
- Accession (2004-0145), 1800s-1990s, 1 boxes
  Addition (2004-0145) (150 items, 0.6 lin. ft.; dated [1800s]-[1990s]) contains a wide variety of promotional items, most dating from the early to mid 20th century, including cookbooks, pamphlets, brochures, direct mailings, order forms, and other items. Also includes a can opener, a contact lens case, an LP record, and two CDRs.
- Accession (2008-0311), 1850-1950, 1 boxes
  Addition (2008-0311) (150 items, 0.2 lin. ft.; dated [1850]-[1950]) includes trade catalogs, booklets, brochures, and leaflets for a wide variety of industries, including books, machinery, and appliances.
- Accessions (2008-0317), (2008-0322), (2008-0323), (8/2014), (2016/0258), 1 folder (interfiled with Acc. 08/311: Box 1
  Addition (2008-0317) (3 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1898) consists of a pamphlet advertising a Commercial Travelers' fair in New York.
  Addition (2008-0322) (3 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1913) includes a letter from Regal Tailoring to J.T. Ryan asking him to represent the company as an agent.
  Addition (2008-0323) (5 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1879) includes 5 pieces about becoming an agent for Sherman & Co.'s Centennial Illuminating Oil and Compound bar soap.
  Addition (8/2014) (4 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1906-1907 and undated) comprises envelopes and printed items related to subscriptions for and advertisements in the Journal of the American Medical Association.
  Addition (2016/0258) (1 item, 0.1 lin. ft; 1933) comprises one business card from the Aryan Book Store in Los Angeles California. Card reads "Truth Brings Liberation."
- Accession (2014-0175), 1 Box
  Scope and Contents
  Addition (2014-0175) (75 items, 0.3 lin. ft.; dated 1890s) includes 75 sachets and sample envelopes for perfumes, talcum, face powders, complexion powders, and soaps manufactured primarily in the United States, with a few from Canada. Almost all the packages are color-lithographed and feature images of women, children, and infants, and sizes range from 2 x 2 inches to 5.5 x 4 inches. Among the sample products are Tetlow's Gossamer for the Complexion, San Toy Talcum, Charles Meyer Black Mascarillo; La Maison Dorin Rouge Framboise, Qentin's Beauty Leaves, Purity Soap Leaves, and Xenobia Sachet. Manufacturers include Jergens, L. H. Pierson, Chapman & Rogers, F. R. Arnold & Co., Puritan Pharmaceutical, Freeman Perfume Co, Henry Tetlow Co., H. G. Schlueter, Bronson Chemical Co., Larkin Co., California Perfume Co, Lightbody & Co., Red Feather Perfume Co., Parfumer Tre-Vaux, Colgate & Co. and Canadian firms Sovereign Perfume Ltd., National Drug and Chemical Company. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture and the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.